<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Puritan convert, not to prelatick Protestantism and yet to prelatick Protestantism, nor to popery and yet to popery, but absolutely and without reserve to apostolical Christianity ..., or, A discourse by way of a letter shewing that prelatick Protestants, if they will be true to their practises and principles, have all reason to turn papists in all things as to what papists indeed hold, but in nothing as to what papists are vulgarly believed to hold ... / by W. H.</title>
            <author>W. H.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3246A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19570562</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19570562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109131</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44852)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109131)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1690:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Puritan convert, not to prelatick Protestantism and yet to prelatick Protestantism, nor to popery and yet to popery, but absolutely and without reserve to apostolical Christianity ..., or, A discourse by way of a letter shewing that prelatick Protestants, if they will be true to their practises and principles, have all reason to turn papists in all things as to what papists indeed hold, but in nothing as to what papists are vulgarly believed to hold ... / by W. H.</title>
                  <author>W. H.</author>
                  <author>Hubert, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 29 [i.e. 31] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC LXXVI [1676]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added t.p. with title: The Catholick naked truth, or The Puritan convert to apostolical Christianity.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to William Hubert.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestant churches --  Relations --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109131:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109131:1"/>
            <p>THE PURITAN CONVERT, Not to Prelatick Proteſtantiſm, and yet to Prelatick Proteſtantiſm; nor to Popery, and yet to Popery; but abſolutely, and without Reſerve, to Apoſtolical Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: That is, to whatſoever Doctrine or practice, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latick Proteſtant or Papiſt can prove, to have been taught the World by the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>OR, A DISCOURSE By way of a LETTER: Shewing, That Prelatick Proteſtants, if they will be true to their Practiſes and Principles, have all reaſon to turn Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, in all things as to what Papiſts indeed hold; but in nothing as to what Papiſts are vulgarly believed to hold: And that <hi>de facto</hi> Non-conformiſts would turn Papiſts, were they not impoſed upon by falſe Principles, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Slanders, deviſed by the firſt Separatiſts from the Church of <hi>Rome. By</hi> W. H.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come and I will teach you how great things God has done for my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Domini</hi> MDCLXXVI. <hi>Permiſſu Superiorum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="second_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109131:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109131:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CATHOLICK NAKED TRUTH. OR, THE <hi>PURITAN CONVERT,</hi> TO Apoſtolical Chriſtianity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:109131:3"/>
            <p>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T why the Naked Truth? Becauſe I deſign a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did. Naked Deſcription of a Puritan, Prelatick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, Papiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I expect the fate of Poor <hi>Robins Adamite:</hi> Some body or other will have a laſh at me. But if I ſcape ſo well as the Author of the Prelatick Naked Truth has done, I hope no blood will follow. To wit, to be <hi>firſt</hi> laſhed by a ſevere Animadverter; and then to be ſtript Naked <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</hi> Had the Candid Author been ſtript first and then whipt, his Caſe had been more pitious. The Animadverter was a little too haſty. A Third I hear has taken him to task, but they ſay he is a more Gentle Whipſter.</p>
            <p>With my Soul I compaſſionate him, as one meerly impoſed upon by Forgeries, and falſe Principles, deviſed by the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and amongſt others, eſpecially by this, that the New Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piure is the adequate Rule of Chriſtian Faith and Worſhip. Go on, Worthy Sir, to Fast and Pray, whilst others Feast and Play at <hi>Lantrelue.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109131:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:109131:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109131:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Firſt Letter.</hi> What the Author means by a Prelatick Proteſtant, Puritan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Deareſt Friends and Neareſt Relations,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is my hearts deſire to ſpeak with every one of you; and to tell you with all Sincerity, what the All Good God has done for my Poor Soul; but the troubleſomneſs of the times, and your great diſtance from one another, not permitting me ſo great a comfort; I have thought fit to communicate to you my good Wiſhes of your Eternal Happineſs by Ink and Paper. Our dear Redeemer, Jeſus Chriſt, Bleſs my Poor Labours to you all, and ſtir up others, who are better able, more fully to inſtruct you in the way to Everlaſting Bliſs; which I know to be the great deſire of your Souls. After the ſearch of many years ſpent in Prayer, Reading, and conference with Perſons of different perſwaſions, I doubt not but I have found out the Truth: Almighty God be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Bleſſed for it. I doubt not but I have found out the True Church of Jeſus Chriſt, the indeed People of God, who walk in the direct Path to endleſs Beatitude; and whoſoever walks, as they walk, and teach, ſhall infallibly ſee God for ever. I confeſs, I am Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from Puritaniſm: But, to what? to Prelatick Proteſtantiſm? No; nor to Popery neither: But to Antient Apoſtolick Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Though indeed, I have not ſo much left Puritaniſm, as Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks call it, as added that to it; wherein I found it (and I hope many of you will find it) come ſhort of the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Doctrine, and Inſtitutions. That you may the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me in my enſuing Diſcourſe, I will briefly Explain to you, what I underſtand by a Puritan, what by a Prelatick Proteſtant, and what by a Papiſt, and what by an Apoſtolical
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109131:5"/>
Chriſtian, which I profeſs my ſelf, by the Grace of Jeſus Chriſt, to be.</p>
            <p>I underſtand by a Puritan, one that being Viſited from Heaven by rouſing checks of Conſcience, could find no Reſt for their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Soul, by living under the liveleſs Miniſtry, and Spiritleſs form of the eſtabliſhed Religion of <hi>England.</hi> One, who by reading ſome portion of Holy Scripture, or other Spiritual Book, or by hearing ſome awakening Sermon, was ſo ſtruck from above, that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his Heart nor Mouth, but that great Queſtion of the man concern: Sirs, <hi>What muſt I do to be Saved?</hi> One, who from the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from on high, had ſo much life in him, as to be ſenſible of the heavy burden of a hard Heart; and whoſe great Prayer to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty was, To take from him his Heart of Stone, and to give him a Heart of Fleſh. No Books, no Company, no Sermons, no Thoughts were guſtful to him, but ſuch as were conducing to the melting and changing of his Heart and Soul. All Lip-labour he deem'd but loſt Labour, ſo long as his Soul within was not chang'd; ſo long as his Heart was hard, he could find no ſatisfaction in words and expreſſions, though never ſo Pathetical, whether uttered by himſelf, or others, or ſet down in Printed Books: Nay, he was ſo far from being ſatisfied with ſuch wordy Devotions, that he was even afraid to uſe them, for fear of being guilty of damnable Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy. For Example, to ſay, or read by way of Prayer; O my God, my All! How I love you! How my Soul is grieved that ever I have offended you! his Conſcience telling him, he had no ſuch Affections, but that his Heart was hard as a very Stone. No re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting of hearty ſorrow for paſt iniquities; no tender reſentments of the innumerable Divine Benefits; no ſtrong hopes of future Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Goods; nor yet affrighting fears of the dreadful day of wrath; Conſcious to himſelf of a great deal of ill paſt, and clear conviction of no preſent good diſpoſition in his Soul, and yet aſſuredly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there muſt ſome good be in the Soul, or no hopes of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Almighty for ever; without holineſs, true Internal Holineſs, Heart-Holineſs, Spirit-Holineſs in this life, no hopes of ſeeing the All Good God in the next. And thus much of a Puritan, I think none that has any ſenſe of a God can miſlike, of whatſoever perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he is, whether he be Papiſt, Proteſtant, or Phanatick. I do not uſe theſe terms to revile, or exaſperate any one; but meerly for diſtinction ſake. And I beſeech my Reader not to be offended at them, if he meet with them now and then in my following Diſcourſe.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109131:5"/>
God forbid, I ſhould willingly anger thoſe wounds, which with my Soul I deſire to cure.</p>
            <p>But what do I underſtand further by a Puritan? I underſtand one, who wearied out with wraſtling againſt the corruptions of his own Heart, ſtill finds much evil in the interior of his Soul, boylings of anger, flames of concupiſcence, greedy deſires of Money, and the things of this life; and however exteriorly refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and changed he may ſeem to be to the World, he's diſ-ſatisfied within himſelf, that he is not changed enough; nor changed enough, I ſay; although his profane Kindred and acquaintance, think him changed but too too much; becauſe he will not, nor dare not Revel it with them as formerly. Inſtead of Plays, and Comedies, his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments now are the Holy Scriptures, or other good Books, written by ſuch who experimented in their own Souls, what they taught others; the works rather of Pious Mens Hearts, than of Learned Mens Brains. Whilſt his Companions are roaring and rally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Tipling Houſes and Taverns, he's ſighing, and groaning in his Bed-chamber, or Cloſet; wraſtling with his offended God by hearty Prayers, according to what moſt preſſes his wounded and afflicted Spirit. He dares not lye, he abhors an Oath as Hell; he is afraid to cheat or cozen any he deals with; though he finds to his grief, but too great deſires of worldly wealth in the bottom of his Heart. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on days ſet apart for the Divine Worſhip, he wiſhes he could keep his Soul wholly fixed upon God. He can by no means ſatisfie his Conſcience, by bearing a part with his Lips only in any forms of Prayer, though in themſelves never ſo holy and good, for an hour or two, and then to ſpend, or rather waſt the reſt of the day in idle talk, diſports and paſtimes, or ſomewhat worſe, Dalliances, Revels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But his employment is to lay up a ſtock of proviſion for his poor Soul to live upon all the week after. Then he labours to renew his firſt repentant ſorrow for his life paſt, and to confirm his weak reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of another kind of life for the time to come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what hurt in all this? if this be to be a Puritan, would to God all the world were Puritans. What need of ſuch a Mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion? Whither muſt he turn? What muſt he change to? unleſs it be from better to worſe. But may he not change from good to better? why, what's wanting in him? That you ſhall hear by and by. Only take notice for the preſent, That I am ſo far from being Converted from thus much of a Puritan, that I moſt heartily wiſh I could Convert all the World unto it. The poor afflicted Puritan,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109131:6"/>
ſadly, and deſervedly affrighted with the fear and apprehenſion of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal damnation, labours and works how he may avoid it: And Beading in the Holy Scripture thoſe words of our Bleſſed Saviour; <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are burdened, and I will refreſh you:</hi> And ſeeing a neceſſity of ſome righteouſneſs or other to entitle him to Heaven, and finding nothing in himſelf but ſin and wickedneſs; and having heard much talk of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and of being ſaved by his Righteouſneſs, and finding ſome places in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſeem to ſound that way, all his care is to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that Righteouſneſs, and to rely upon what Jeſus Chriſt has done and ſuffer'd for him: And by this means he begins to deem him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a ſecure condition. By the Blood of Chriſt thus apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and applied by a lively Faith, he grows very confident and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all the fire of Hell is quenched as to him, and he fears damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no longer: And though unworthy of his Heavenly Fathers Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction for any thing in himſelf, yet appearing before him in the Garments of his Elder Brother, he doubts not of a Bleſſing, and that an Eternal one too. And this conceit if it do not make hm very bold to ſin, at leaſt it makes him very negligent in adorning his Soul with Piety, Charity, Meekneſs, Patience, Humility, and other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertues; partly thinking them impoſſible to be attained; partly deeming there is no abſolute neceſſity of them to his Salvation: He having nothing to do, but to believe that Jeſus Chriſt has done all for him, and what Love, or Piety, or other Vertue neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from ſuch a Faith, he willingly admits: but for the reſt, ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly to endeavour after the acquiſition of Vertues, he looks upon as the working of an Old Teſtament Spirit, and a derogation from the perfect Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, and his Righteouſneſs. The Old Covenant was, <hi>Do this and Live;</hi> but now he is under a better Covenant, <hi>Believe and Live,</hi> or <hi>Live and do this.</hi> The impreſſion his firſt awakening has left upon him, keeps him from returning to open lewdneſs and profaneſs; but his Faith of this imputative Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt, makes him take little pains in the cultivating of his own Soul, either in purging it of the Relicks of ill habits, or in planting in it the Divine Vertues, our Lord Jeſus taught us to exerciſe, by his Word and Example. And this is our Puritans firſt miſtake; and a dangerous one too, as I ſhall ſhow afterwards.</p>
            <p>His next miſtake is; he begins to quarrel with all Exterior Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Ceremonies. And he falls into this miſtake by reflecting upon his own Experience, as having reaped no benefit by forms of Prayer,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109131:6"/>
by Bowing at the Name of Jeſus; by looking upon certain days as Holy-days, and Faſting-days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hence he begins to think, all ſuch Obſervances are wholly uſeleſs and unprofitable, if not abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and ſuperſtitious beſides. And he is much confirmed in this his Imagination, by conſidering the open profaneſs, and little ſenſe of God, he obſerves generally in zealous Conformiſts. Moreover, on the other ſide, he takes notice of his Brethren Non-Conformiſts, that they are generally free from open and ſcandalous ſins, and at leaſt ſigh and breath after Interior Spirit and Devotion, which certainly muſt be that muſt give us a Title to Heaven, rather than a few crin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or Exterior Verbal Devotions, which any one, though never ſo Profane, may eaſily exerciſe; and indeed he ſees with his Eyes many do Exerciſe, who give no Teſtimony at all of any work of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in their Hearts; but by their profane, light, and vain Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, give too clear evidences of their being ſtill in their natural un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate condition. And accordingly their Preachers in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have little life or zeal; and ſeldom diſcourſe of ſuch Truths, as are apt to awaken Mens Conſciences, and make them lay to Heart the great concern of the Salvation of their Souls: Or if they do at any time Preach of Judgment, or Hell; Repentance, or a New Life; they do it very coldly and imperfectly, and ſeem to talk like Parrots what they have learnt by rote, and out of others Books, and not what they have had any Experience of in their own Hearts. Such Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, joyn'd with ſome places of the New Teſtament not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood, make him think, that whatſoever was pleaſing to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, or profitable to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People under <hi>Moſes;</hi> Now we that are under the Goſpel, muſt be Spiritual Worſhippers, if we will be Worſhippers in Truth, and muſt caſt away all Exterior forms of words, and outward obſervances of days and places, as hindran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to True Spiritual Goſpel-worſhip. And all agreeing, that the Body of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law is aboliſhed, with its Prieſthood, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, ſpecial Garments in time of Divine Worſhip, particular days to be kept Holy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This being confeſſed by all, as well Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants as Papiſts, and finding no clear expreſs mention in the New Teſtament of any Exterior Rites, (except a very few) appointed by our Bleſſed Saviour, or his Apoſtles; no Holy-days, nor Faſting-days, no particular Garments for Prieſts, no ſet forms of Prayer for them, or the people, except one little ſhort one, commonly called <hi>Our Lards Prayer;</hi> and deeming that the New Teſtament was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to inſtruct us Chriſtians in the whole Body of Goſpel-worſhip,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109131:7"/>
as the Old Teſtament was written to inſtruſt the <hi>Jews</hi> in the <hi>Moſaical</hi> manner of Service: Our well-meaning Puritan makes no doubt, but all <hi>Ember-days, Vigils, Lent-Faſt, Chriſtmas-day, Good-Friday, Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Whitſontide,</hi> &amp;c. are meer humane Inventions, a meer Will-worſhip; the blind obſervers whereof can expect no other reward, at the day of Account, but that ſharp check; Who has required theſe things at your hands? inſtead of a, well done Good and Faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, enter into the Joy of thy Lord, which they vainly expected for a toilſom obſervance of a company of burdenſome Ceremonies of their own deviſing. And this I underſtand by a Puritan.</p>
            <p>By a Prelatick Proteſtant, I underſtand one, who agrees with the Puritan in this, that he expects Salvation by the extrinſecal Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt without him, not by any interior Righteouſneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his own Soul. Though ſome of the Prelatick Clergy begin to ſcoff at the Doctrine of Imputative Juſtice. One of them lately in a Sermon before His Majeſty, called it, and not improperly, <hi>The Mummery of Imputative Juſtice.</hi> As if he would tell us, that an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putative Holy Man, is a meer Chriſtmas Mummer, who to little Boys and Girls ſeems a Prince in his aſſumed Bravery; but Perſons of years and underſtanding, ſee under his borrow'd Regal Attire, a poor Cobler, or ſorry Botcher; or like the Daw in the Fable, who had made himſelf very gay with the fine Feathers he had ſtoln from other Birds; but when each Bird, being to appear before their King in their proper Array, ſnatcht back their ſtoln Feathers; the poor Daw, that had made himſelf fine with anothers Bravery, became the common object of ſcorn and laughter. Such will be the ſad Lot of meerly Imputative Saints, who to themſelves, and their Brethren, ſeem very fine, in the extrinſecal Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, put on by their Phantaſtical Faith, whilſt God and his Angels, under all this conceited, aſſumed Bravery, ſee a laſcivious, wanton, or a covetous Miſer. But if the Prelatick Proteſtant and Puritan agree in the Doctrine of Imputative Juſtice, wherein do they differ? Has the Prelatick Proteſtant no terrors of Conſcience upon him, as well as the Puritan? Generally ſpeaking, Prelatick Proteſtants (I wiſh it were a ſlander) are very profane, and give no ſigns of any Interior trouble of Conſcience. And if any of them begin to be heartily troubled for his ſins, he is obſerved either to turn Fanatick, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt; that is, either to practice what he profeſſes, as to Holy-days, and Faſting-days, Confeſſion of ſins to a Prieſt, and ſuch like Rites, wherein he agrees with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> or elſe to turn Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109131:7"/>
and ſcoff at all ſuch obſervances, as Legal, mimical, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious. But whilſt he continues Proteſtant, in what differs he from the Puritan? why, he is very angry with the Puritan, that he will not abſtain from Fleſh in <hi>Lent,</hi> upon <hi>Fridays, Ember-days,</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils</hi> of Saints: Though practically ſpeaking, no body takes leſs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them than himſelf: Only on the <hi>Sunday</hi> before, as the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſter of the Great God in <hi>Pontificalibus,</hi> in time of Divine Service, he advertiſeth the people of ſuch and ſuch days of Abſtinence, and Faſting, as occurr: And the poor Puritan, becauſe he will not ſolemnly invite the people to obſerve, what himſelf never intends to take the leaſt notice of, muſt for this be ſilenced, and ſuſpended both from Office and Benefice. Again, the Prelatick Proteſtant, he won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Puritan ſhould ſcruple the Adorning the Communion Table with two Wax Tapers, thereby to proclaim before God and Man, that he is of that Church, which in the Primitive times for fear of perſecution, ſerv'd God Almighty by Candle-light in Dens and Caves. And the ſimple Puritan thinks it all one ridiculous, to have Candles upon his Table, at noon day unlighted, as lighted; Nay, of the two, it ſeems to him greater non-ſence to have them unlighted. For that the Papiſts who light them, may pretend Ornament and Increaſe of Splendor: But to have them there, and not to light them, no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count can be given, unleſs it be for that it is leſs expenſive. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the Prelatick Proteſtant wonders, what hurt the Puritan can ſee in making the Sign of the Croſs, upon the Fore-head of a new Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd Infant; though even he ſmiles at a Papiſt, when he makes it upon himſelf, or his Victuals; which the Puritan can by no means underſtand. If our Lord Jeſus, ſays the <hi>Non-Conformiſt,</hi> would have Chriſtians Croſs their Children, in memory of his dying upon a Croſs; I cannot think it credible, that he ſhould prohibit them to Croſs themſelves, upon the ſame account. Or if he muſt be wiſe above what is written, he thinks he may as well credit the Papiſt, who ſays, He has a Tradition for Croſſing himſelf; as the Biſhop, who ſays he has a Tradition for Croſſing his Children. The Prelatick Proteſtant wonders the Puritan can doubt, the Holy Euchariſt (as he begins to call it) is really and truly the Body of Chriſt? ſince our Bleſſed Lord ſays ſo plainly of it, at his laſt Supper, <hi>This is my Body.</hi> Why then ſhould any one doubt of the Feal Preſence of our Saviours Body, where himſelf ſays it to be? Or why ſhould any one refuſe to Adore upon his Knees his Bleſſed Saviour, under whatſoever form or ſhape, he ſhall pleaſe to repreſent himſelf unto him; provided it be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109131:8"/>
himſelf really, truly and indeed, as here none can doubt him to be, having his own infallible word for it. And why he may not appear to us in the form of Bread, after his Aſcenſion, as well as he appeared to St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> in the ſhape of a Gardiner, after his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>M. Thorndike</hi> cannot underſtand. Nay. Dr. <hi>Coſins</hi> in his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Traenſubſtantiation</hi> goes yet further, and ſays, <hi>Pag.</hi> 44. <hi>It is not queſtioned, whether the Body of Chriſt be abſent from the Sacrament, duly Adminiſtred according to his Inſtitution, which we Proteſtants neither af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm nor believe: For it being given and received in the Communion, it muſt needs be that it is preſent, though in ſome manner veyled under the Sacrament; ſo that of it ſelf it cannot be ſeen.</hi> And Pag. 117. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants do freely grant, and firmly believe, That the Wine (as hath often been ſaid) is changed into the Blood of Chriſt; but every change is not a Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Now the Puritan wonders how any of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief can boggle at the Popiſh Tranſubſtantiation, or change of Bread, in the Holy Communion, into Chriſts Body. If there be no change at all made in the Bread and Wine, ſays the Puritan, either by Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, or Popiſh Conſecration; without all peradventure there can be no Real Preſence of Chriſts Body. The ſame remaining the ſame, without any change, muſt needs be the ſame. But if there be any change made; in Accidents, its evident there's none; our Senſes, and all Popiſh Doctors confeſſing as much. If therefore there be any change, it muſt be in the ſubſtances of Bread and Wine; and if ſo, what can ſuch a Change be more properly called, than Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation? or the change of the ſubſtances of Bread and Wine, into the ſubſtance of our Bleſſed Saviours Body and Blood, the accidents of figure, taſt, and colour remaining unaltered? The Prelatick Proteſtant wonders, that the Puritan, when he is going out of this World, ſhould find difficulty to make a particular Confeſſion of his ſins, if any grievous matter lye upon his Conſcience; and humbly deſire the Prelatick Prieſts Abſolution, ſaying over him after his ſpecial Confeſſion: <hi>By the Authority of Jeſus Chriſt committed to me, I Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve thee from thy ſins, in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The Puritan replies; if Jeſus Chriſt has Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any ſuch Ordinance, he ſees not why every one ſhould not fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent it every year, or as often as he finds himſelf conſcious of any heynous crime with the Papiſt. But Jeſus Chriſt having Inſtituted no ſuch Right or Sacrament, he wonders any dare be ſo bold to preſs it upon any Chriſtian living, or dying; and indeed leaſt of all dying: when ſure, if ever, we ought to have a care, not to ſeek to pleaſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109131:8"/>
Almighty God, by unpreſcribed Will-worſhip, or Inventions of our own. Moreover, the Prelatick Proteſtant wonders at the Puritans Niceneſs, that he can by no means be perſwaded to Bow at the Sacred Name of Jeſus; when Nature teaches us a Relative Reverence to any thing that has a Relative Reſpect to a Perſon whom we Honour: Every one without ſcruple ſtanding bare in the <hi>Preſence-Chamber;</hi> nor does any one paſs the Kings Chair of State without a Reverend Bow, whether His Majeſty be there or no. And the ſimple Puritan deems it as groſs Idolatry to worſhip Sounds, as Colours; Names, as Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures; and ſtranges, that any one who does ſo ſuperſtitiouſly cringe and bow at the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſhould ſmile at a Papiſt for reſpectful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly putting off his Hat, when he paſſes by the Picture of the ſame <hi>Jeſus.</hi> The ſound of the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> being vaniſh'd and gone, before the ſuperſtitious Worſhipper can make his Mimical Congy, whereas the Picture, a far more lively Repreſentation of the ſame Great Lord is permanent, and remains to receive its Devout Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Relative Reſpect. The <hi>Conformiſt</hi> wonders what there is in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent White Surplice, that ſhould boggle the skewiſh Puritan: And the Puritan admires how any one can think a Surplice ſhould become a publick Miniſter of the Divine Worſhip, and yet throw away, as Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biloniſh Rags, the Popiſh Girdle, Stole, and Caſuble, which add Splendor and Decency to the ſame unwritten ſuperſtitious Garb, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be becauſe they are more chargable. The <hi>Conformiſt</hi> wonders at the Puritans ſcrupuloſity, that he cannot ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> to that Prayer in the Burial of the Dead: That we with this our Brother, and all other departed in the true Faith of thy Holy Name, may have our perfect Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation and Bliſs, both in Body and Soul, <hi>&amp;c. We muſt pray for the Dead,</hi> ſays the Rector of <hi>St. Martins</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> in his Sermon called the <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Puritan. Thy Kingdom come, O Lord raiſe the dead Priſoners in the Grave. And herein we pray for their Souls and Bodies. God be with them to comfort their Souls deprived of their Bodies.</hi> And to the Puritan this ſeems plain Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. In fine, the Prelatick Proteſtant wonders at the Puritans pride, that he will not ſubmit his Judgment in matters of Faith, to the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Council of all the Reverend Biſhops of the Land, His Majeſty as ſupreme Head and Governor preſiding: And the Puritan is amazed, that if we may pin our Faith upon another mans ſleeve, &amp; ſafely believe, as a particular Church in <hi>England</hi> believes; how it can be unſafe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ones judgment to the determination of a General Council of all the Learned Biſhops of the Chriſtian world, his Holineſs the Pope as ſupreme Paſtor preſiding, &amp; believe as the Univerſal Church of Chriſt believes. 'Tis
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109131:9"/>
fitting, ſays the Conformiſt, that for order ſake, in Chriſts Church there ſhould be in every Nation ſome ſupreme Governors, to whoſe Directions, in matters of Divine Worſhip, all ſhould ſubmit, elſe we ſhall have as many Chriſtian Religions, and ways of Worſhip, as there are Pariſhes; nay, as there are private Families, or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons. The Puritan replies; if we muſt conclude our Lord Jeſus governs his Church, as our reaſon tells us it's fitting he ſhould, for Union, Decency, and Order govern it, and not according to the infallible written Rule of the New Teſtament: If the Caſe be this; It ſeems to him as rational, that he ſhould for the ſame Reaſons of conſerving Union, Decency and Order in his Church appoint one ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Paſtor over all Chriſtians diſperſed in all the Nations of the World, whom all ſhould obey in the vacancy of General Councils, for fear forſooth otherwiſe, there ſhould be as many ways of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Worſhip, as there are ſeveral Chriſtian Kingdoms, of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths. I ſpeak not this to revile the eſtabliſhed Religion of the Nation, but to excite the Profeſſors of it to obſerve devoutly, what they Chriſtianly profeſs, as to Holy-days, <hi>Lent, Fridays,</hi> and other Faſting-days, Confeſſion of ſins to a Prieſt, and other Holy and Profitable Rites, when Piouſly, and Reverently performed, and by which they are diſtinguiſhed from Non-conformiſts.</p>
            <p>And by this time I hope, <hi>My Deareſt Relations,</hi> you underſtand what I mean by a Prelatick Proteſtant. But what do I underſtand by <hi>Popery,</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt?</hi> Why what ſhould I underſtand by a Papiſt, but what the generality of people underſtand by a Papiſt; Thoſe things we call Stones, which every body commonly ſpeaking calls Stones; and ſo I underſtand by Popery and a Papiſt, what every body commonly ſpeaking calls a Papiſt and Popery. By a Papiſt then I underſtand one, that worſhips Stocks and Stones, Medals, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and other Saints, as Gods, and conſequently prays to them, and puts his whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in them; as the ancient Heathens did in their dumb Idols of <hi>Jupiter Mars,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay one that worſhips Pictures of Jeſus Chriſt, as Gods: Not barely one that has ſuch Pictures, and for pious purpoſes alſo, for that Prelatick Proteſtants have as well as they. Proteſtants have Pictures of Jeſus Chriſt and his Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not only in their private Houſes, and publick Churches, but even, their very Common-Prayer Books are full of them in the laſt Impreſſion, to excite in the Beholders mind a lively apprehenſion of our. Bleſſed Saviours life and death. Nor can I think, they that are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109131:9"/>
ſo ceremonious in devoutly Bowing, when they hear the Holy Name of their Saviour Jeſus, can forbear in ſome devout fit, eſpecially thoſe of the tenderer Sex, from kiſſing the Picture of their ſame deareſt Lord. But here's the difference betwixt them and the Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Papiſt: That the Papiſt Bows at the Name of Jeſus, and kiſſes his Picture, with a deſign to give Divine Honour to the very Name and Picture; but our Prelatick Proteſtant does the ſame thing, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending only to give them civil reſpect, as he would give to the Name or Picture of his King, Furthermore a Papiſt is one that believes the Pope can give him leave to commit any ſin for Money; or if any one were ſo bold to commit the ſin before he got leave to commit it; 'tis but giving ſo much Money, and the ſame Holy Indulgent Father can ſo perfectly pardon your ſin, as you ſhall not be in the leaſt danger of any puniſhment for it, Temporal or Eternal, in Purgatary or in Hell: And all this, though you have no purpoſe at all to forſake your ſin. And this his Holy Father can do by a plenitude of Power, which he has of diſpoſing and applying to whom he pleaſes, penitent or not penitent, the ſuperabundant merits of Jeſus Chriſt our Bleſſed Saviour and his Millions of Saints, of all whoſe merits the Pope is ſupreme Lord to diſpoſe of them to the living or dead, as he by his un-erring Spirit thinks fitting. I ſay to the living or dead? for this Papiſt believes, that the Pope can free, what Souls out of Purgatory he pleaſes, paying their debts for which they are there in priſon, out of the ſtock of the ſupererrogatory works of Saints: Always provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that in lieu or rather purchaſe of ſo great a favour, ſome of the deceaſed parties friends give a large alms to his Holineſs. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the Papiſt Honours the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> much more than he does her Divine Son or God the Father; and therefore for one Prayer he makes to God, he ſays ten to the Holy Virgin. But alas what are his Prayers? A company of Latin words he neither underſtands, nor cares to underſtand, which if he do but patter over in ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, though his mind and heart be wholly taken up with worldly thoughts and deſires, he thinks he has done ſuch a meritorious work, as God almighty is obliged for the great Honour he has done him to give him Eternal Happineſs. If he do but believe as his Churchmen believe, though he be wholly ignorant of their Belief, his Soul is ſafe enough.</p>
            <p>Beſides, he makes not only Gods of Holy Men departed, but even of ſinful Men whilſt they live. Hence he makes leſs ſcruple of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods Laws, than he does of violating any Ordinance of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109131:10"/>
Pope, or any Law of his Church. He muſt by no means touch the leaſt bit of Fleſh on a Faſting-day, againſt his Churche's Law, upon pain of damnation; but if he commit Fornication, 'tis but a Venial ſin, and ſprinkling himſelf with a little Holy Water, he's as pure from all ſpot as a new Baptiz'd Infant. And as for obedience to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, if they be not of his Religion, he ows them no Allegiance: And it he have by Oath obliged himſelf, he has a Holy Father can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with him for that or any other Oath for a piece of Money. If his Prince perſecute him for his Religion, let him but have ſo much deſperate courage to Sacrifice his own life, to Stab or Poiſon his ſaid Perſecutor, he ſhall at <hi>Rome</hi> be Canoniz'd for a Saint. Nor can private perſons expect any fidelity from him, when he is thus traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly rebellious againſt his Liege Lord and Soverain. Therefore whatſoever promiſe he has made to an Heritick, he may lawfully break it, and cheat and cozen him without any ſcruple: Nay, need make no more difficulty of killing an Heritick, than of a common Highway Man. As for Faſting and Mortification, if he but abſtain from Fleſh, though he drink all day long the beſt Wines he can get, fill himſelf at noon with all variety of Fiſh, and ſtuff himſelf again at night with all ſorts of Sweet-meats, he has like a good Chriſtian piouſly and ſorrowfully commemorated the bitter death and paſſion of his dear Redeemer; he has done a work of a ſtrange force to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for his ſins, to ſuppreſs his corrupt inclinations, to elevate his mind to Heaven, to caſt out the Devil, to obtain the Holy Ghoſt for himſelf or others. As for Virginal Purity, if he do but make a Vow of Chaſtity, and keep himſelf from Marriage, though he be as familiar with Nunns as Lay People are with their lawful Wives; he is one of the Virgins in the Myſtical Book of St. <hi>John,</hi> who follow the Lamb whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever he goes. As to Pardons &amp; Indulgences 'tis wonderful what he believes. For a round Sum of Money paid to his Holy Father the Pope, he can purchaſe a Pardon for himſelf, and his Heirs for ever, for whatſoever ſins he or they may poſſibly commit. Sins that are to be committed by himſelf twenty years hence, or by his Poſterity a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years hence, he has a Pardon for them already in his Pocket, under the Broad Seal of Chriſts Vicar upon Earth: which our Lord Jeſus nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can nor will deny, but has engaged his infallible word to ratifie and confirm and all this, though the Perſons who have obtained this Pardon or Indulgence ſhould chance to dye without the leaſt Remorſe or Repentance for their ſins. And by this the World is taught to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what a Bleſſing it is to have a great Eſtate, for that Rich Men
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109131:10"/>
who have but Mony to purchaſe one of thoſe Pardons, can never fail of Heaven; whereas the Poor, and thoſe of ſlender Fortunes, for want of them, muſt be hurried away into Eternal Miſery, without Bail or Mainprize. Moreover, by vertue of theſe Pardons, they have leave to commit all manner of villanies without ſin, or at leaſt without any danger of receiving any prejudice by ſin, Theſe Papiſts they'l tell you indeed, their Church is a Holy Church, and has all means imaginable to ſuppreſs vice, and encourage to ſanctity. They have a Hell to ſet before audacious ſinners, to terrifie them from committing mortal and grievous offences, and they have a Purgatory with which they threaten leſſer offenders. But in very deed both their Hell and their Purgatory, are ſo eaſily avoided by any one that has a little Money, that he muſt be one that ſtartles at his own ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that can at all be terrified by either. For had you committed all kinds of ſins imaginable, if you have but the Impudence to tell your Ghoſtly Father all thoſe villanies in his Ear, though you be ſo far from reſolving to amend, as you ſecretly purpoſe when you have clear'd the old, to begin a new ſcore, provided you do but profeſs to your ſaid Confeſſor, that you are ſorry and ſay you will amend, he by three or four words in Latin, <hi>Ego te Abſolvo,</hi> &amp;c. By the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Jeſus Chriſt I Abſolve thee from thy ſins; does as perfectly free you from all obligation to Eternal Torments, as if you had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſinn'd. And as for the temporal pains in Purgatory, which may be due to you for want of a true ſorrow, and a hearty purpoſe to amend, 'tis but ſaying Seven <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and as many <hi>Ave Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> upon ſuch a Saints day in ſuch a Church, and you go ſtrait to Heaven clear from all ſpot and ſtain. There are many more ridiculous abſurdities which this ſadly deluded Papiſt believes and practiſes, but theſe I think are ſufficient to make any Man in his wits to abhor Popery as the greateſt piece of Non-ſenſe imaginable. And underſtanding by Popery, what has been ſaid (and yet that is not half of that Ridiculoſity, which the Generality of people in <hi>England</hi> underſtand by it) he that ſhould turn Papiſt, be he for Religion, <hi>Proteſtant, Jew</hi> or <hi>Turk</hi> he muſt certainly for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding be a Mad Man, Child or Fool, either one that has loſt his wits, or one that is not yet come to his wit, or one that never had, nor ever ſhall have any wit.</p>
            <p>But were not our Anceſtors here in <hi>England</hi> for many ages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all Papiſts? Are not whole Nations, <hi>France, Spain, Italy</hi> and others generally Papiſts? Have we not ſome thouſands of Papiſts ſtill
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109131:11"/>
remaining in our own Countrey. Are all theſe Children, Fools or Mad Men? Let them look to that. You and I are ſure that no Man that has half the underſtanding of a Man, can think that ſuch a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of ridiculous Tenets and Abſurdities, can look like any ſuch thing as a Religion revealed from Heaven: And if they confeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Papiſts, and to hold thoſe witleſs abſurdities; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion unavoidably falls upon them. They muſt be Children, Mad Men, or Fools. Unleſs you will ſay, they know well enough all thoſe ridiculous abſurdities, how irrational and ſenſeleſs they are, as well as you and I; but for temporal ends, in their Hearts being of no Religion at all, they make a profeſſion of believing and revering all the above-mentioned Fopperies. And this I muſt confeſs is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrange folly in theſe Papiſts, and a contradiction not to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel'd in the moſt blockiſh uncultivated <hi>Indians.</hi> For the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Riches, Honours and Pleaſures of this life, they make a ſhow of believing moſt ſeriouſly a thouſand abſurdities, which they laugh at in their Hearts; and yet they are ſo ſenſeleſs, as they'l looſe their Lives, Eſtates, Dignities and all, rather than abjure thoſe very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities. Further, They are ſo aſhamed of their doltiſh Religion, that charge them with any of their ſtupid opinions; and they'l pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs by all that's Sacred, they neither believe, nor practice any ſuch things, as you lay to their charge. And yet you and I know moſt aſſuredly that they do in the very bottom of their Hearts ſo ſtrongly adhere to them, that they would part with Life and all that's deareſt to them, rather than forego them. But how come you and I to know they hold ſuch and ſuch abſurd fancies, they ſo conſtantly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing they hold no ſuch thing? Can any body know their minds and practices better than they themſelves? That's a conſiderable Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and ſhall be anſwered afterwards. Sure if this be their Caſe: That indeed they do not Worſhip and Pray to Pictures, and Stocks and Stones as Gods, nor believe any ſuch extravagant power in their Holy Father at <hi>Rome</hi> to pardon or give leave to commit ſin for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and a thouſand other abſurdities, which commonly they are charged with: And yet they will rather endure all loſſes of Eſtate, Liberty or Life, then relinquiſh the ſaid deteſtable abominations, methinks they do not deſerve ſo much to be perſecuted, ſequeſtred, impriſon'd, hang'd drawn and quarter'd for Traytors, as to be pitied and caſt into <hi>Bedlam</hi> for Mad Men, or to have their Eſtates begg'd for Natural Fools. There is ſome Myſtery lies hid here, which we have not yet diſcovered. Either they are groſly and ſtupidly miſtaken in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109131:11"/>
matters of Religion, or elſe we are ſtrangely miſtaken in them, and what is indeed their Religion.</p>
            <p>But for Gods ſake, as you deſire our Eternal Wellfare, which you ſeemed in the beginning of your diſcourſe ſo heartily to pretend unto; of what Religion are you your ſelf, who write thus for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your deluded Puritanical Kindred and Acquaintance, whom you ſo pity and compaſſionate? If you be neither <hi>Puritan, Prelatick Proteſtant,</hi> nor <hi>Papiſt,</hi> what are you? A <hi>Jew, Turk,</hi> or <hi>Pagan?</hi> No, I thank the All Good God I am a Chriſtian; An <hi>Apoſtolical Chriſtian.</hi> That is, one that believes whatever Doctrine can be proved to him, to have been taught the World by the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt: One that admits of any practice introduced into the World by the ſame Apoſtles: One that reverences all Books or Writings, as of an in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Divine Authority left by them. Nay, if the Holy Apoſtles left any in Commiſſion as their Succeſſors, to make Ordinations obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable by all Chriſtians, I receive all Decrees of ſuch Delegates of the Apoſtles alſo But theſe are general terms, what do you believe in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular as to the Worſhip of God in this World, and the ſtate of departed Souls in the other, and ſuch line controverted points betwixt Papiſts and Proteſtants? Do you believe all thoſe Papiſtical Doctrines you mentioned above or no? I thank my God, there's not one of them, which I do not deteſt as Hell it ſelf. But what do you poſitively believe? I do believe whatſoever Jeſus Chriſt taught his Twelve A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and what his Twelve Apoſtles taught the VVorld. And I do believe Almighty God has left us who live in this Seventeenth Age from our Dear Saviour, certain and infallible means to know what they taught the VVorld in that firſt Age in which they lived; at leaſt ſo much of what they taught and eſtabliſhed as is needful for us to know and practice, to diſpoſe us for Beatitude in the other life. For that otherwiſe the univerſal Redeemer, ſhould not have been a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Saviour of all the VVorld, but only of that part of it, which had the happineſs to live in that firſt Age of Chriſtianiſm; or at moſt only of ſuch Ages as were ſo near that Primitive Happy Time, that they could certainly and infallibly know what Truths were taught, and what practices in order to the bettering, to the preparing of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind for Heaven, were ſet on foot by Jeſus Chriſt, or his infallible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates, Subſtitutes or VVitneſſes.</p>
            <p>But what means has Jeſus Chriſt left us at this diſtance from the time wherein he illuminated the VVorld by his Divine! reſence, to know how he lived, and how he taught his followers to live to come
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109131:12"/>
to Eternal Life. Has he in ſome ſtrange Iſland, preſerved ſome Hundreds of Venerable Old Men, who have been kept alive ever ſince that firſt Age, to teſtifie to all Generation, what kind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin they had heard with their Ears, or what kind of Worſhip they had ſeen with their Eyes, taught and eſtabliſhed by the firſt Planters of Chriſtianity? No, I know no ſuch thing. Though this would have been a ſtrange favour to the World, would the Almighty Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor have wrought ſuch a Miracle in favour of Ignorant Man. But what then? Did Jeſus Chriſt after the manner of <hi>Moſes</hi> write a Book of all Chriſtian Rites and Obſervances, or did he not at leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſome one of his Twelve Apoſtles, or all of them together to write ſome ſuch Book, ſo full, ſo compleat, ſo plain, as none that would not willingly miſtake could poſſibly miſ-underſtand it? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he could not but foreſee, what diſputes would ariſe about obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of Days and Sacraments amongſt Chriſtians in future Ages. Why did he not tell us plainly by ſome Authentick Writing or other: His pleaſure was, that all the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Rites and Obſervances of Days ſhould be aboliſhed, and inſtead of them he would have no Exterior Rites and Days at all; or elſe if he would have any, why did he not take care that ſome Book or other ſhould be written, wherein every one that could read might ſee, how many Rites called Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he would have to be uſed amongſt Chriſtians, and how and to whom, and by whom he would have them to be adminiſtred? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would have certain days obſerved by Chriſtians in memory of his Birth, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion or no; any ſet days of Faſting, any diſtinction of Garments in Prieſts from the People or no? But himſelf to write never a Book to this purpoſe, nor any of his Apoſtles to write any thing but his Holy Life and Death four times over, and ſome little of the Life of ſome one or two of his Apoſtles, and a few occaſional Letters of two or three of his Followers to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Chriſtians, whom they had fully inſtructed by word of mouth; what can we conclude from all this? But that ſurely Jeſus Chriſt has left us ſome other means, than thoſe written Books we have, fully to inſtruct us in the whole Counſel of God in Order to our Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Indeed I find an Ancient Propheſie, that in the latter days God Almighty would write his Laws in his Peoples Hearts. Was this to intimate to us, that whoſoever would find fully and clearly the Laws of Jeſus Chriſt in the latter days, he muſt not ſo much conſult written Books as the Hearts of Chriſtians? And truly there is no other way without a miraculous Revelation by the Miniſtry
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109131:12"/>
of Angels, or ſome ſuch means, for us who live now to know what was taught or practiced ſixteen hundred years before we were born, but only by Books written in that time or near that time, or elſe without Books by the oral Tradition of Fathers to their Children.</p>
            <p>But what Certitude can there be in this? Could we ſpeak with every Father and Son that has lived ſince the Apoſtles days, and ſhould they tell us unanimouſly, that they had been taught to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and practice thus and thus: For Example, to Baptize Children or not to Baptize them, to abſtain from Fleſh on <hi>Fridays</hi> or not to abſtain in memory of our Lords bitter Death and Paſſion, and to humble our ſelves for our ſins, and ſuch like; no body could doubt of the truth of ſuch a Teſtimony, more than he does miſtruſt his own Eyes or other Senſes? But all the intervening Fathers and Sons 'twixt us and the firſt Age wherein our Lord Jeſus lived, except only our Fathers and Grandfathers, being gone to another World; my Grandfather can tell me certainly what his Father taught him concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Faſting on <hi>Friday,</hi> Baptizing of Infants, Reverencing ſuch a Book as of Divine Authority, written by a Holy Man talled <hi>Mathew</hi> ſixteen hundred years ago; but what aſſurance can he give me, that all his Progenitors have practic'd and believ'd after the ſame manner ever ſince the Apoſtles days? Why, what aſſurance could a <hi>Jew</hi> that lived in our Bleſſed Savioms time, have given to a Pagan, or to one of his own Children, that the Books of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> were written by a Holy Man called <hi>Moſes,</hi> who familiarly converſed with God, ſo many hundred years ago? He could only have diſcourſed to him after this manner. Thus I was told by my Father, and thus all our Neighbouts were told by their Fathers, and 'tis impoſſible in any Age ſince our Great <hi>Moſes,</hi> all our Anceſtors ſhould agree together to tell their Poſterity ſo great a lye, to their own, and their Poſterities Eternal damnation. One Man may tell an impudent notorious lye, but a whole Countrey cannot conſpire in a lye which they know to be a lye; or could they, ſome neighbour Nation would tell the Cheat to Poſterity. In like manner muſt the Apoſtolical Chriſtian anſwer, when he is demanded an account, why he reveres ſuch and ſuch Books as Apoſtolical writings, or obſerves ſuch and ſuch Rites as Apoſtolical Ordinations. And this is the belief and practice of an Apoſtolical Chriſtian in general. VVhatſoever this preſent Age, or any other Age ſince the Apoſtles time in ſeveral Nations and Countries, unanimouſly atteſt that they have received from their Forefathers from the Apoſtles, and he cannot poſitively ſhow that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109131:13"/>
it was of a later date: begun for Example in or near ſuch a time, by ſuch and ſuch, he ſubmits to it as Apoſtolical; and this though it cannot poſitively be proved, that, for Example, ſuch a Book or Practice was received in every Age ſince the Apoſtles days, by poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Teſtimonies out of Authentick writings of every particular Age. And thus much ſatisfaction and no more could <hi>Jacob</hi> have given to his Children, why he kept the Sabbath day, commanded by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to our firſt Parent <hi>Adam</hi> above two thouſand years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. He had neither Scripture nor other Record of writing for any ſuch Inſtitution, the uſe of writing being unknown to the world till afterwards, when God Almighty wrote the Ten Commandments in Two Tables of Stone. He could only tell them, thus he and his Neighbours had been immemorially taught to believe. And their objecting, how could they tell but ſome body out of a ſuperſttious opinion of more Sanctity in every ſeventh day, than in every ſixth or eighth, might have introduced the will-worſhip of ſuch an Obſervation; ſuch an Objection, I ſay, as this, would not have excuſed them before God from ſuch an Obligation, which the whole preſent Generation told them they had obſerved immemorially from <hi>Adam.</hi> And indeed, though it were granted that according to the Holy Scriptures, we Chriſtians are obliged to keep every firſt day of the week Holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet it cannot be proved out of Scripture or any other Book, or by any other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the immemorial tradition and practice of ſeveral Chriſtian Countries, that the day we now obſerve is the true firſt day of the week, from that firſt firſt-day on which our Bleſſed Savour roſe from Death to Life. And yet that there ſhould be Chriſtians who ſhould make no diſtinction betwixt <hi>Friday</hi> and the other days of the week; though, go into all the Chriſtian Countries of the world, and you'l not find one before <hi>Luther,</hi> but ſay they have immemorially from the time of the Apoſtles abſtained from Fleſh upon it in memory of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviours bitter Death and Paſſion. I fear me at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their pleading they found no ſuch command in all the New Scripture will be no ſufficient excuſe. If others faſt not as they ſhould do upon that day, muſt I therefore think I am excus'd from faſting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as I ſhould? No more than I am excus'd from laying aſide my worldly Affairs on <hi>Sunday,</hi> and ſpending it in Holy Exerciſes, becauſe others profane it by drinking and diſports. But this by the way only.</p>
            <p>As to the ſatisfaction of that conſiderable Queſtion above, How we ſhould know what the Papiſts believe and practice better than themſelves, at leaſt better than they will tell us what their belief and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109131:13"/>
practice is, as to praying to Images, buying Pardons and Licences to commit ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I muſt tell you plainly, I have lived above 20 years amongſt them, and I could never yet meet with ſo much as one ſingle perſon, that believ'd or practic'd any one of all thoſe ſtupid abſurdities I mentioned in my Deſcription of a Papiſt; and the truth is, there is not one ſuch Papiſt in <hi>England,</hi> nor any where elſe, but in Proteſtants Brains and falſe Imaginations. Nor do I deſire any one ſhould credit me as to this particular, nor the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church neither, but let him ask the firſt Papiſt he meets, whether he pray to Images or no; believe the Pope can give him leave to commit fornication for a piece of Money or no <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if the firſt Papiſt he meets with will acknowledge no ſuch thing, let him propoſe the ſame queſtions to the next he meets, and ſo to others, until he find one: or if he can find none, let him not for Phraſes in printed Books which he miſ-underſtands, ſlander his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Neighbours. We eaſily miſ-underſtand one anothers wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, but when we diſcourſe together we explain our ſelves what we mean by ſuch and ſuch Expreſſions, which at the firſt hearing cauſe a wrong underſtanding in us. And I eaſily perſwade my ſelf would thoſe of ſeveral Perſwaſions in our ſadly divided Countrey, familiarly and friendly converſe together, and ask an account of each others belief and practice, we ſhould ſoon if not be of one mind, at leaſt ſo far be of one Heart, that it would be far from us from thinking of perſecuting one another to death for our differences in points of Religion. We ſuppoſe the <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> hold ſuch and ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities, and then here I can have you, and there I can have you againſt the Wind-mills of our own Brains. Would Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> or others who write againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when in ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Author they meet with ſome Doctrine or Practice which ſhocks their underſtanding with its (as it ſeems to them) ridiculouſneſs and abſurdity, but reflect that there are great numbers of perſons of ſound Judgment and Vertuous Lives, who believe and juſtifie all Doctrines and Practices truly Catholick; methinks they could not but ſuſpect; ſurely I either miſ-underſtand this Author, or elſe its only his private opinion, and conſequently he alone, and not the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Church ought to have dirt caſt in her face for it, or or elſe they have ſome Reaſons for ſuch a belief or practice unknown to me; and therefore before I write againſt it, I'le conſult ſome Romaniſt of judgment and underſtanding about it, who by word of mouth can more plainly declare the ſaid Doctrine or Practice, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109131:14"/>
their Reaſons for it, if it be indeed owned and juſtified by their Church. Such candid ſincere dealing as this would cut ſhort many of our diſputes, and ſtrangely conduce to a happy compoſure of all our differences. And indeed had we a deep ſenſe of one anothers Eternal Happineſs and Miſery, and ſtrong hearty deſires of rightly informing one another in the direct paths to Eternal Beatitude, we would do ſome ſuch thing, rather than miſconſtrue one anothers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ſayings, and lye at the catch to make picquant re-parties upon each other, as we do.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>my dear Relations,</hi> to give you an account of that ſtrange and hardly credible, and yet moſt certain truth, <hi>viz. That you living amongſt Papiſts, and converſing daily with them, nay and often diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with them about Religion too, yet do quite miſtake their Religion, and do not at all underſtand what they either believe or practice as to their way of Worſhip, but imagine a thouſand fopperies and madneſſes concerning them, which they no leſs than your ſelves abhor and deteſt with their Hearts.</hi> To give an account of this ſtrange Paradox. Should an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> tell a <hi>Turk</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> Sir, I come out of a Countrey, where we are not all of one Religion, and for this cauſe, the ſupreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates perſecute thoſe of a different perſwaſion from them, and all this meerly through a miſtake, becauſe they miſ-underſtand one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The perſecuting party fancies that thoſe whom they perſecute hold the moſt ſtupid opinions in matters of Religion, that ever were held by Men: worſhip Stocks and Stones as Gods, pray to them, put their confidence in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> think they can have leave from their Chief Prieſt, whom they call their Pope, to commit any ſin for money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is all the abſurdities I mentioned above; and yet notwithſtanding not one Man of all the diſcountenanced party, holds ſo much as one of all the Abſurdities with which he is charged, but is ready by all that is Sacred to abjure them all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and every one in particular? What think you would a ſtranger imagine, to whom ſuch a Narration ſhould be made? would he not Reply? Surely you do not ſpeak all one and the ſame Language, or elſe if you do, you ſeldom or never diſcouſe with one another about matters of Religion, or elſe you are are a ſtrange blockiſh people, who cannot underſtand common ſenſe; or elſe the diſcountenanced party are Men of no Conſeience, and therefore when you demand an account of them concerning their Religion, they make no ſcruple to believe in their Hearts one thing, and to ſwear to you they believe quite contrary: but then one would think they might abjure their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109131:14"/>
whole Religion, and conform Exteriorly to the Religion eſtabliſhed, and ſo avoid the penalties of the Laws in force againſt them; or elſe the Ruling Power gains a conſiderable Revenue or ſome other nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advantage, by diſcountencing diſſenters from them in matters of Religion. No. Pecuniary Mulcts as they are, through the favour of a Gracious Prince exacted, add nothing at all to the publick Treaſury, and the whole force of the Nation is far leſs formidable to Externs, than otherwiſe it would be, were it not for our diſ-union amongſt our ſelves. What then is the true Reaſon, you neither can nor will underſtand one another? No body is malicious againſt his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, meerly becauſe he will be ſo, when he is not only no gainer by his malice, but alſo prejudiced by it, which notwithſtanding if I underſtand you aright, is the ſtate of your Countrey. What muſt we ſay in this caſe to ſatisfie a ſtranger to our Affairs? Why, I would tell him the plain truth: That is, About a hundred and fifty years ago we were all of the preſent diſcountenanced parties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligon, but the Supreme Power thinking fit in many things to change, or as they phraſed it, to reform the way of worſhip taught them by their Anceſtors, partly aggravated real abuſes, which ſtood in need of correction, and partly calumniated with a thouſand lies thoſe who would not joyn with them in their pretended Reformation, and thoſe lyes have been propagated from Fathers to Sons ever ſince. Moreover there is a Real and very Conſiderable difference as to divers points, betwixt the Religion eſtabliſhed by Law, and the Religion of diſſenting Papiſts, as we call them: Eſpecially about Tranſubſtantiation, Invocation of Saints, and Purgatory: And now you know people of different perſwaſions, are very apt to ſlander and miſ-underſtand one another, hoping thereby to make their own cauſe more plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Beſides, thoſe of the eſtabliſhed Religion having the free uſe not only of the preſs, to write whatſoever they pleaſe concerning the diſcountenanced party, but alſo having the command of all the publick Pulpits, in which every week they repreſent their Adverſaries how they pleaſe to the whole people, no body being permitted to gainſay or contradict them, nor even to write any thing but by ſtealth; and after all, their Apologies for themſelves come into the hands but of a very few: And it being very unreaſonable to perſecute with loſs of Eſtate or Life, good and peacable Subjects purely for their Conſciences in matters of Religion, and this about ſome nice Points only; the Ruling Party (or rather the firſt Reformers) to juſtifie their own ſevere Laws againſt diſſenters, are forced to ſlander them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109131:15"/>
with a thouſand lies before the vulgar Multitude, who eaſily believe what is told them by their Miniſters, eſpecially if they be ſuch as they Reverence for their ſeeming learning and good life. Nor do I by what I am a ſaying accuſe the whole preſent Clergy of lying againſt their Conſciences, when they tell the people that Papiſts pray to Stocks and Stones as Gods, can have pardon of ſin paſt, or leave to commit ſin to come for Money. No, I believe many of them do really think ſo in their Hearts, having been often told ſo from their Infancy, and knowing little of Papiſts but from printed Books, and theſe made by their Adverſaries too. But the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers who had been educated in Popery, could not but lye againſt their Conſciences, when they told the people ſuch lies concerning Papiſts as I have made mention of above. In like manner new Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Prieſts muſt needs have very bad Conſciences, when they accuſe, as they do, Papiſts of ſuch things, as their own Conſciences tell them, themſelves were not guilty of when they were Papiſts. For Example, the Author of that Scurrilous Pamphlet, <hi>The Rates of ſins in the Cuſtom-houſe of the Church of</hi> Rome: What Conſcience could he have? when he could not but fore ſee that the common people would thence be confirmed in their miſ-belief concerning their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Neighbours, that they can have pardon and leave to commit any ſin for Money, which in his Conſcience he knew to be moſt falſe. And yet after all, one that had a mind to vilifie the Church of <hi>England,</hi> might with the like ſemblace of Truth, Intitle a Book, <hi>The Rates of ſins in the Cuſtom houſe of the Church of</hi> England, and make good the Title by ſetting down the Pecuniary Mulcts which are exacted in Biſhops Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Courts for Adulteries, Fornications, Diſpenſations in Marriages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> you might have leave to commit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery for ſo much, and Fornication for ſo much, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when all this while, theſe are only Pecuniary Puniſhments by which the Eccleſiaſtical Power diſcountenances, and endeavours to prevent ſin and wickedneſs. And yet what hurt do ſuch Paltry Pamphlets the ſimple half-witted Multitude? Jeſus have Mercy on the Authors of them. But I am giving an account of our miſ-underſtanding one another in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>Add moreover, that Papiſts do practice certain things which thoſe that are either very ignorant or very malicious may eaſily make a bad conſtruction of. For Example, they moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay their Prayers kneeling before ſome Picture of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, or his Holy Mother, or ſome other Saint; hence half-witted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that have often heard that Papiſts worſhip Images as Gods, do
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109131:15"/>
really think they pray to the Picture they kneel to God Almighty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. When if you ſaw their Hearts, or would believe their Tongues, they are as far from adoring ſuch a Picture as God, as <hi>Socrates</hi> was from worſhipping the Clouds, as the common people imagin'd, when they ſaw him bow his Body to the Creator of all in the open fields: And do no more pray to Pictures than you do to the bare walls, or Communion-Table ſet Altar-wiſe, you kneel before when you are at your Prayers. What you do to your Communion-Table, or to the Name of Jeſus, that they do to the Picture of the ſame Jeſus, and no more. And would you without paſſion and partiality converſe with them, you would find what I ſay to be moſt true. To illuſtrate what I am a ſaying, give me leave to inſert a pleaſant Story told me by a Proteſtant Lady. It ſeems in a Church in Town, certain Gentlewomen (and theſe oftentimes but a quarter-pac'd Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, as the Animadverter upon <hi>Naked Truth</hi> phraſes it) ſit very near the Communion Table, or half-pac'd Popiſh Altar; now Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough-pac'd Conforming Ladies entring the Church, ſhow their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect towards the Holy Table, by making a low Reverential Court'ſy: the Gentlewomen that ſit near the Superſtitious Altar, taking all that reſpect as done to themſelves, wonder much at it, and whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to one another; Madam, Is that Lady of your Acquaintance? No. Nor of yours Madam? No. Surely ſhe either knows, or thinks ſhe knows ſome of us, ſhe ſo civily ſalutes us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Madam; you miſtake; 'Tis not to you, but to the Holy Euchariſt, which is wont to be diſpenſed from the Sacred Table you ſit ſo near; the Devout Lady gives all that reſpect. Juſt ſo fares it with the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Papiſt, who paſſing by the Image of his Dear Crucified Lord, Reverently pulls off his Hat, or Reſpectfully Bows his Head. The half-witted Proteſtant having been told from his Cradle that Papiſts worſhip Stocks and Stones as Gods, now believes the Papiſts to be Idolaters, not becauſe his Miniſter told him ſo; but becauſe he has, as he thinks, been an Eye-witneſs of their Idolatry; when all this while the Devout Romaniſt ſhows all this reſpect not to the Carved Wood or Stone, or painted Cloth or Paper he bows before, but to his great Lord Jeſus in Heaven, repreſented by thoſe Figures. Put all that has been ſaid together, and you will ſee there is no great wonder in it, that the commonalty of our ſadly divided Countrey ſhould believe a thouſand lies in matters of Religion, concerning their Catholick Neighbours, eſpecially if you add that thoſe who have been about 150 years ſlandering of them, have withall told the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109131:16"/>
vulgar, that Catholicks are ſuch a cunning and deceitful people, that you may not believe them in one word what they ſay to you concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Religion, but being aſham'd of their Fopperies, they will deny them if you lay them to their charge: Or if at any time you meet with any whoſe candor and ſincerity you are ſo convinced of, that you cannot think he would tell you a lye: Then you muſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine him to be of a particular belief and temper from all other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, and though he hold no ſuch abſurdities by reaſon of his better underſtanding, learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet the generality of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple moſt certainly hold them all. O the craft and cunning of the Devil and deceitful Men, thus to blind and miſerably impoſe upon the ſimple and well-meaning vulgar! Jeſus of his Mercy open their Eyes, and make them ſee who they are that thus ſadly delude and cheat them. Beſides the Laws being very ſevere againſt Catholicks, many are afraid to have a better opinion of them than they are taught to have, though they even ſee they are much ſlandered, leſt they ſhould be convinced of the truth of their Religion, and then be obliged either to damn their Souls if they would not embrace it, or looſe their Eſtates and Preferments if they did embrace it. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, Catholick Religion is a Holy and Strict Religion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no wonder if the Profeſſors of it be hated and ill ſpoke of by the wicked and looſe world. Libertines willingly ſpeak ill of thoſe that are ſtrict and very conſcientious in their ways, but being aſhamed to revile them for their Vertues, (though that be the real quarrel which they have with them) they miſ-interpret their innocent and good Actions, and calumniate their perſons with a thouſand ſlanders. For Example. Catholick Religion teaches, that if any one have wronged his Neighbour by cheating, cozening or ſtealing any thing from him, he's bound if he be able under pain of damnation to make reſtitution, and without this no Tears, no Prayers, no Faith in the Blood of Chriſt can ſave him. The ſame Religion teaches alſo, that you are bound under pain of damnation to confeſs your moſt ſecret ſins to a Prieſt, and that if you be truly penitent, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to lead a new life, upon the Prieſts abſolution on Earth you are moſt certainly pardoned in Heaven. It teaches alſo, that you have a like obligation to abſtain from Fleſh in <hi>Lent</hi> and upon other days of Abſtinence, <hi>Fridays, Vigils,</hi> &amp;c. Now Fleſh and Blood does not like theſe Reſtraints. And hence thoſe that have no mind either to make Reſtitution of ill gotten Goods, or to diſcover their ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſins to a Prieſt, or to abſtain from Fleſh on certain days, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109131:16"/>
that Prieſts when people confeſs to them, enjoyn them to make Reſtitution, and if they be not able to faſt, enjoyn them oftentimes to give Alms in lieu of it, and in ſuch caſes diſpenſe with the Eccleſiaſtical Law of Abſtinence; this is ground enough to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate poor Papiſts, and to tell the ſimple Multitude, that they can buy pardon of their ſins for Money, and have leave from their Prieſts to break any Law of God for Money, and let them commit what villanies they pleaſe, 'tis but confeſſing them to a Prieſt, and this without any repentance, or purpoſe of Amendment. <hi>Miſereor ſuper turbam.</hi> What Chriſtian Heart would it not make to bleed to ſee how the well-meaning Multitude are abuſed and impoſed upon by their deceived Guides?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Dear Relations,</hi> For the love you have to your Immortal Souls, do your ſelves that right as but familiarly to converſe with your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Neighbours, and with as little paſſion as you can, do but ask them an account of their Religion, and do not againſt all common ſenſe and reaſon, believe the Teſtimony of their Adverſaries concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them and their Religion, rather than them themſelves, and if you do not find that you have been taught a thouſand lies concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, and that they hold nothing nor practice nothing but what they are able to give a very ſatisfactory Account of to any impartial Enquirer, then ſay I am a Knave, a Lyer, and a Cheat, one that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves no Mercy from God or Man, in this World or the next; but if you find what I have ſaid to be moſt true, pray for thoſe that have deceived you, and think ſeriouſly what it behoves you to do, and whetehr you have not reaſon to ſuſpect thoſe Church-men, who ſtand in need of ſuch notorious lies and ſlanders thereby to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt their Adverſaries. If Popery be ſuch a doltiſh and ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Religion, then what need of belying it and ſlandering it to make it odious to the People? and what fear of Its overſpreading the Nation by a free and unlimited Toleration? But the truth is, it's a Holy, and moſt rational Religion, and ſuch as Men muſt ceaſe to be Men, or they cannot but acknowledge the Finger of God in it, when it is duly and truly repreſented as it is in it ſelf, devoid of all thoſe fopperies and lies with which it is calumniated by its Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. For the love of God, what Papiſt in the world believes that the Goſpel is but a Fable of Chriſt; that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is a God; Not any ſin, but is or may be indulged amongſt them, and ſcarce a known ſin but there is a known price for it, and at their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-rate you may commit them when you will, that they allow
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109131:17"/>
Whoredom all the year long, and the practices of other unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes not to be named among Men in ſome Months of the year; that mortal ſins are put away by <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> by little parcels of the Goſpel, by Popes and Biſhops Pardons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That Chriſt is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of Men only, but of no Women, for Women are ſaved by St. <hi>Clare</hi> and Mother <hi>Jane:</hi> That the Pope may check when he pleaſes the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and controul any thing avouched by all the Apoſtles: That we muſt ſimply believe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it teach true or falſe; and if the Pope believe there is no life to come, we muſt believe it as an Article of our Faith? What Papiſt in the world believes one of all theſe Madneſſes and Blaſphemies? and yet the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Church is charged with them all, by no leſs a Man than the preſent Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York;</hi> if that Book be his Grace's, which is commonly ſold in <hi>London</hi> with his Name to it, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters alſo, under the Title of a <hi>Manul of Active Poſitive, and Oppoſitive Divinity;</hi> written by him to preſerve a Noble Lady from the danger of Popery. I confeſs a Proteſtant to whom I read a Dialogue in that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unal</hi> ſaid, Surely ſome body to diſgrace his Lordſhip had Printed it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Name: But on the other ſide it is not credible that a Book ſhould be publickly ſold, all over <hi>England,</hi> for four years together, under ſo Great a Perſons Name and yet be none of his, if there were any thing in it his Lordſhip was aſham'd to own. I well foreſee what I have written will be ill taken by many, but I dare not but diſcharge my Conſcience, and profeſs as in the ſight of God, I wtite not thus to diſgrace any Mans Perſon, but meerly to diſ-abuſe my well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Relations, who I am ſure have ſuch a Zeal of Godlineſs, and true Sanctity, that they would love Papiſts and their Holy and ſtrict Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with their Hearts, were not they and their Religion miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto them. To defame a particular Perſon is a great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but to ſlander a whole Church is a Detraction of a higher rank, and aſſuredly does oblige the Detractor to revoke his Calumnies. God be merciful to us; we have faults but too too many, what need of belying one another? Let us believe one another what we ſay our Tenets of Religion are, and diſpute againſt thoſe, and not againſt the uncharitable ſurmizes of our own Brains. To judge my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to be guilty of moſt horrid Blaſphemies, when they proteſt they abhor them no leſs than my ſelf, if this be not to Judge my Neighbour, which is notwithſtanding moſt ſeverely prohibited me by my Bleſſed Saviour, I know not what is. Now for a Grave Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to accuſe not ſome private Authors, but the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Church
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109131:17"/>
of all thoſe Blaſphemies and Abſurdities, I but now mentioned, and yet not that ſo much as one ſingle Papiſt you can meet with will own ſo much as one of them, I am at a ſtand what to think. Surely no Man could be ſo malicious to write ſuch things on purpoſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe a poor Lady; and on the other ſide to think that a Doctor of Divinity could be ſo ignorant of the Tenets of Papiſts, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that no body can be a Papiſt, but he muſt neceſſarily believe the Pope is a God, that he may have leave to commit almoſt any ſin at a known price when he will; that the Goſpel is a Fable <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Had he in plain terms told the good Lady, ſome <hi>Roman</hi> writers as he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them, or as Proteſtants cited them, held ſuch and ſuch Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and Blaſphemies, but not one Papiſt ſhe could meet with would own ſo much as one of them; this would have ſignified nothing to the retaining of her in the Proteſtant Communion. For the Reply would have been eaſie: Either you miſ-underſtand the Authors, or elſe they are at moſt but the phrenſies of ſome particuler Men, and conſequently I may be a Papiſt and hold none of them, but abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and deteſt them all. But that he might be ſure to preſerve the Lady from the danger of Popery, under the diſguiſe of a Dialogue, he makes a Papiſt give for Reaſons why he cannot become Proteſtant, the Blaſphemies and Abſurdities above; which is as much as to tell her, if ſhe will turn Papiſt ſuch and ſo Blaſphemous muſt her Faith and Religion be. Methinks knowing many of his Catholick Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to be Men of good Judgment and honeſt Converſation, he ſhould have demanded of them, whether ſuch things were generally believed by them or no, before he had printed them as Reaſons, why a Papiſt could not change his Religion: for if one may be a ſound Papiſt and hold none of them, then all his Lordſhips diſcourſe falls to the ground, whatſoever ſome particular Doctors may hold concerning them. Though that alſo be a meer calumny, and ſhould any be ſo extravagant as to aſſert ſuch Diabolical phrenſies, he would be caſt out of our Church as a Blaſphemer.</p>
            <p>And that you, <hi>My Dear Relations,</hi> may ſee that I have not at all wronged the Doctor, I have thought fit to tranſcribe ſome few Lines out of his 7th. <hi>Chap. Page</hi> 101. The next to his Dialogue. <hi>The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Sixth Chapter,</hi> ſays he, <hi>gives an account of ſome of the Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Abominations of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, many more might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced,</hi> &amp;c. Where in plain terms, as before under the diſguiſe of a Dialogue, he charges not barely ſome particular Authors, but the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and all <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks with the Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109131:18"/>
in the foregoing Dialogue. He goes on; <hi>Where is their Piety towards God, while they affirm that the Goſpel is but a Fable of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nay even that the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>is a God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Where is their Sobriety and Chaſtity, while they Authorize Stews, allow Whoredom all the year long,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Scarce a known ſin but there is a known price for it; and at their Market-rate you may commit them when you will,</hi> &amp;c. Such extravagant Diſcourſes though they may hinder ſome from ever examining the Catholick Religion, yet they are oftentimes, God Almighty out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhooting the Devil in his own Bow, happy occaſions of the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of others. I remember to have read of a <hi>German</hi> Count, who reflecting how divers of his Catholick Neighbours were Perſons of a very ſound Judgment and Underſtanding, he began to think with himſelf, how they could believe ſuch ſtrange Doctrines, as were by his Miniſters commonly laid to their charge, hereupon he reſolved to inquire into their Tenets, and he found for a great part they held no ſuch Doctrines as they were commonly taxed with, and as for what they did indeed hold, they had very good Reaſons for their Faith. And ſo by the merciful Grace of God became a happy Convert to that Religion, the which before he impartially examined it, ſeem'd ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otick and incredible unto him. Which I hope, <hi>My Dear Relations,</hi> will one day be your happy lot alſo. Take but pains candidly and diligently to inquire and I doubt not but it will. But if you will needs go on to think your Catholick Neighbours to be ſuch Monſters of Men, and to hold ſuch horrid Blaſphemies and Abſurdities, which they profeſs no leſs to abhor and deteſt than your ſelves, I hope I have done the duty of a Chriſtian Kinſman, and to my grief muſt one day bear witneſs againſt you, that I told you how groſly you miſ-apprehended the True Worſhippers of Chriſt, but you would neither believe me, nor ſeriouſly uſe any means to inform your ſelves aright. But I hope better things concerning you.</p>
            <p>Another great cauſe of all your miſtakes is the ſcandalous lives of too too many <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks. For the truth is, no Catholicks believe ſo much as one of the above-mentioned Abſurdities, yet many of them (Chriſt Jeſus mend us all) live ſo as they may ſeem to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced beholder, to believe divers of them, Conſidering their Mock-prayers, Mock-faſts, and Mock-confeſſions without any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to help you againſt this, you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Counſel of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> to caſt your Eyes not only upon the Cockle, but alſo upon the good Wheat, and if you will needs be comparing the Profeſſors of our ſeveral Religions together, do not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109131:18"/>
compare the beſt of your own Religion with the worſt of ours, but the beſt of ours with the beſt of your own, and the worſt of ours with the worſt of your own; and do not conſider how little our Faſting-days, or Holy-days, or Confeſſion of ſins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> conduce to Piety as they are obſerved by the Libertines of our Church, but what helps they would be to make all the world better, were they obſerved in a due and Chriſtian manner. Another great cauſe of your miſtakes is, that great Lye deviſed by the firſt Reformers, <hi>viz.</hi> That the New Teſtament is a Compleat Rule of Faith and Manners for all Chriſtians. Hence whatſoever Practice or Ceremony you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find there, you reject it as a Superſtition and Will-worſhip. And this makes you quarrel with all Abſtinence from certain kinds of Meats on Faſting-days, and with all Holy-days except <hi>Sundays,</hi> with the Sign of the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas Chriſtian Doctrines and the Evangelical way of Worſhip were firſt taught the world by the Apoſtles before they writ any thing at all. Nor did ever any of the Apoſtles or all of them together go about to write a Book of the whole Body of the Chriſtian Law, like to thoſe of <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticus</hi> written by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as is manifeſt to any one that conſiders the Nature of the Books of the New Teſtament. The four Goſpels are a Hiſtory of our Bleſſed Saviours Life and Death, who lived as to the External Rites of Religion according to the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewiſh</hi> Law, and ſo we cannot reaſonably in any of them expect, what Holy-days or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting days or Ceremonial Rites we Chriſtians are to obſerve in the time of the Goſpel. Indeed had the Acts of the Apoſtles been intended as an exact Narration how the Apoſtles lived as to the whole courſe of their life, what days they kept Holy, and what they faſted, and how; and what Sacraments they adminiſtred, and now, and with what Rites, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we might reaſonably have expected there ſome mention of <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> and <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> of <hi>Lent</hi> and Abſtinence from Fleſh on <hi>Fridays,</hi> of Renouncing the Devil, and the Sign of the Croſs in Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But that Holy Book making mention only, of ſome few particular paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, of two or three of the Apoſtles lives, the Apoſtles might well keep divers Holy-days beſides <hi>Sunday,</hi> and abſtain from Fleſh in <hi>Lent</hi> and upon other Faſting-days, and uſe the Sign of the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and teach the ſame alſo to their firſt Converts, and yet there be a profound ſilence of them in the Book of their Acts. As for St. <hi>Johns</hi> Prophetical Book, it looks nothing like a Ritual, or an Account of what days and Rites in the Divine Worſhip are pecular to us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. The reſt of the New Teſtament are Epiſtles, or Letters of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109131:19"/>
Spiritual Counſel, written by St. <hi>Paul</hi> or ſome other Apoſtle to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons already inſtructed in the Chriſtian way of Worſhip. And why they ſhould make mention therein of all Chriſtian Exterior Rites and Days, I underſtand not, unleſs perchance the Perſons they wrote un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to had been deficient in ſuch Obſervances.</p>
            <p>The Adequate Rule of our Faith and Manners are the Doctrines and Practices taught the World by the Apoſtles of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. And the Holy Scriptures are an Excellent, but not the only means whereby we may aſſuredly come to know what Truths were taught, and what Practices were ſet on foot over the whole Earth by by the ſame Apoſtles. We muſt conſult the immemoral Faith and Practices, and unanimous atteſtations of ſeveral Chriſtian Countries, and what they joynly witneſs immemorally to have received from Father to Son from the Apoſtles, whether it be a Book written, as they tell us, by the Apoſtles, or a Doctrine taught by them, or a Ritual Obſervance ordained by them, we ſafely ſubmit unto it as Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. For that the ſeveral Chriſtian Inhabitants all over the World could never poſſibly meet together to forge a lye. And it is no ſmall cauſe, <hi>My Dear Friends,</hi> of all your miſtakes, that you conceit you know the Holy Scriptures to be the infallible Word of God by their own light. There's no doubt but any one that reverently reads thoſe Holy Books cannot but acknowledge that there are very many Excellent Truths declared in them, but that every thing in them is infallibly true, and that they were written by Men un-erringly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the Holy Ghoſt, it's not poſſible we ſhould ever have come to know ſo much, but by the teaching of our Parents, who from our Infancy imprinted upon us a Reverence to thoſe Sacred Writings above all others. And did we but reflect that the aſſurance we have that the Books of the New Teſtament were written by Apoſtolical Perſons, is only this, that ſo all Chriſtian Countries ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles have immemorially believed, our Diſcourſe would ſtrait tell us, there's all reaſon we ſhould ask of thoſe ſeveral Countries from whom we have received thoſe Divine Books, in what ſenſe they have been always taught to underſtand them? and interpret them accordingly; and what Rites and Obſervances they received together with them? and admit them with the like Reverence. And it will be hard to give an Account to our Bleſſed Saviour, why with ſuch awful dread you ſubmitted to the four Goſpels or Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul</hi> as moſt Sacred and Divine, and yet dared to reject as ſuperſtition and Will-worſhip certain Practices and Obſervances delivered to you by the ſame Hands
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109131:19"/>
immemorially from the Apoſtles. Miſtruſt not the Providence of our Dear Redeemer, he has in all Ages had a Watchful Eye over his Holy Church, not permitting her to Apoſtarize by Idolatry, or be defiled with Superſtition, or to deliver to poſterity her own Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for Apoſtolical Traditions. But more of this hereafter. Till you hear further from me, my Deareſt Friends, let me only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this favour of you, to do your ſelves this right, to converſe familiarly with Roman Catholicks, and to hear impartially what they have to ſay for themſelves wherein they differ from you, and not to fancy they believe a thouſand Abſurdities, which they no leſs deteſt than your ſelves.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours ever. <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
